Finding Aid for Comprehensive Cancer Center (University of Michigan) records
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Comprehensive Cancer Center (University of Michigan) records 1988-2005
University of Michigan. Comprehensive Cancer Center.
07104 Bimu 2
The University of Michigan Comprehensive Cancer Center (UMCCC) acts as an environment for collaboration between research and clinical care for cancer patients of all ages and provides patients with comprehensive diagnostic, treatment and support services. The UMCCC record group ranges from 1988-2005 and consists mainly of photographs and negatives of physicians, researchers and staff, events, the construction of the building. Some publications, news clippings, and limited administrative files are included.
10 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (Donor # 9857 ) was received from the unit in February 2007.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The Comprehensive Cancer Center (University of Michigan) records are open without restriction.
The University of Michigan Comprehensive Cancer Center (UMCCC) was formally established in 1986, with Max Wicha appointed as director. UMCCC was named a Center of Excellence at the University of Michigan Medical Center and received its comprehensive designation by the National Cancer Institute in 1988 for meeting strict guidelines for extensive, innovative research focused on the development of new treatments as well as cancer prevention and control, and a dedication to providing patient education, community outreach and training for health professionals. Home to the most cancer diagnosis and outpatient treatment for adults and children, UMCCC remains committed to the conquest of cancer through innovation and collaboration between scientists and clinicians to achieve superior and compassionate patient care; scientific and technological innovation in cancer research, prevention, control, and treatment; and excellence in training cancer researchers and health care providers.
In 1988, UMCCC received a $30 million donation towards a new building. The UMCCC nine-story building opened in May 1997, four floors devoted to outpatient care, the rest for research laboratories. This new building placed patient care and research side-by-side in the same building, facilitating communication between specialists and the quick transfer of research findings into the clinic.
There are 11 clinical programs from multiple departments and divisions on campus, including: breast, childhood cancers, cutaneous, endocrine, gastrointestinal, gynecologic, head and neck, leukemia/lymphoma and blood and marrow transplantation, prostate/urologic, psychological and neurological oncology, sarcoma, and thoracic oncology. UMCCC also features five basic science research programs and two prevention and control research programs.
UMCCC offers a comprehensive array of supportive services, including a Patient Education Resource Center (PERC), Complimentary Therapies, Nutrition Counseling, Child and Family Life Services, Art Therapy, and Social Work Services. Physicians and researchers are supported by a team of volunteers, including many cancer survivors. UMCCC has approximately 350 physicians/researchers who receive over $82 million in annual total grant funding. In 2005, the UMCCC ranked among the top 10 cancer centers nationally in research funding from the National Cancer Institute.
The University of Michigan Comprehensive Cancer Center (UMCCC) records (10 linear feet) (1988-2005) document the founding of the center, major events, and the doctors and staff members. UMCCC records consist of publications produced by the center, photographs, slides, and negatives of major events, the construction of the center, and doctors and staff members. Other materials, news clippings, and some limited administrative files. The record group is arranged into seven series: Administrative Files, Center Publications, Clippings, Negatives, Slides, Photographs -- Individuals, and Photographs -- Topical.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Comprehensive Cancer Center.; Cancer--Research--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Cancer--Treatment--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Medicine--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Cancer--Michigan.; Cancer--Nursing.; Cancer--Patients--Care.; Cancer--Research.; Cancer--Treatment.; University of Michigan. Comprehensive Cancer Center.; Wicha, Max S.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Administrative Files
  Administrative Files (0.5 linear feet) (1988-2000) contain scattered annual reports and executive summaries, articles on UMCCC, brochures and pamphlets, news releases, and writings on the early history of the center.
  - Annual Reports 1997-1998 (Box 1)
  - Articles About CCC (Box 1)
  - Brochures, Pamphlets, Invitations (Box 1)
  - Conference and Fair Participation 1995-2000 (Box 1)
  - Executive Summary 1993-1994 (Box 1)
  - News Releases 1988-1997, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Simpson/CCC Early Year Histories (Box 1)
- Center Publications 1990-2005
  Center Publications (0.5 linear feet) (1990-2005) include scattered serial publications: Ad vance, Michigan Oncology Journal, Progress and Update. Michigan Oncology Journal is published three times per year and features articles written by researchers and physicians, where each issue typically focuses on one disease type or treatment approach. Progress was the Cancer Center's external newsletter, and Update was the Cancer Center's bimonthly internal newsletter. Scattered copies of Advance, the University of Michigan Medical School's journal, are found in the record group. There are also three monographs: "Building Our Strengths," "Guides for Patients," and "Prospectus."
  - Advance, 1991-1995 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - "Building Our Strengths," 1992 (Box 1)
  - "Guides for Patients," 1998-1999 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Oncology Journal, 1990-2001 (scattered), 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Progress, 1990-2005 (scattered), 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Prospectus (Box 1)
  - [Comprehensive Cancer Center] Update, 1997-2001 (scattered) (Box 1)
- Clippings
  Clippings (3 linear feet) include 10 binders of news clippings from 1989-2004 and original clippings from 1993. Clippings feature stories related to UMCCC and its programs, from newspapers and journals both in Michigan and nationally.
  - 1997-1999, 3 volumes (Box 2)
  - 1989-1996, 4 volumes (Box 3)
  - 1993 Originals (Box 3)
  - 2000-2004, 3 volumes (Box 4)
- Negatives 1993-1996, 1999-2001
  Negatives (1.75 linear feet) (1993-1996; 1999-2001) are arranged chronologically by date and are many times individually labeled by event or publication date. Many of the negatives are of images featured in UMCCC Progress and Update. Folders are labeled with individual names and events.
  - 1993-1996 (Box 5)
  - 1999-2001 (Box 6)
- Slides
  Slides (0.25 linear feet) (undated) include slideshows of presentations on a range of topics, including cancer facts, prevention and education, outreach, clinics, patient support services, research, network, and mission. Other topical slides include the construction of the UMCCC building, publicity, signage, and survivorship.
  - CCGG Slides at BMC, 1 volumes (Box 6)
  - Slideshow, 1 volumes
    - Cancer facts (Box 6)
    - Prevention and Education (Box 6)
    - Outreach (Box 6)
    - Clinics (Box 6)
    - Patient Support Services (PSS) (Box 6)
    - Research (Box 6)
    - Network (Box 6)
    - Mission (Box 6)
  - Topical
    - Building Construction (Box 6)
    - Signage (Box 6)
    - Survivorship (Box 6)
    - Publicity (Box 6)
- Photographs-Individuals
  Photographs -- Individuals (1 linear foot) (undated) are arranged into individual folders labeled with the names of researchers and staff. Many photographs are headshots, while some are featured in publications found in this record group. Photographs include founding director Max Wicha, as well as other UMCCC directors such as Alfred Chang, Eric Fearon, Ken Pienta, Marcy Bohm Waldinger, and Gregory Wolf.
  - Adler (Box 7)
  - Baker, Larry (Box 7)
  - Balcueva, Ernie (Box 7)
  - Biermann, Sybil (Box 7)
  - Boxer, Laurence (Box 7)
  - Brenner, Dean (Box 7)
  - Carson, Eric (Box 7)
  - Castle, Val (Box 7)
  - Chan, June (Box 7)
  - Chang, Alfred (Box 7)
  - Clark, Mike (Box 7)
  - Cooke, Kenneth (Box 7)
  - Cooney, Kathy (Box 7)
  - Cooper, Carlton (Box 7)
  - Crowley, Shelia (Box 7)
  - DeRoeck, Martha (Box 7)
  - Dixon, Suzanne (Box 7)
  - Dworzanin, Lynn (Box 7)
  - Dwyer, Shon (Box 7)
  - Erba, Henry (Box 7)
  - Esper, Peg (Box 7)
  - Fader, Darrell (Box 7)
  - Fearon, Eric (Box 7)
  - Ferrara, Jamie (Box 7)
  - Foley, Sally (Box 7)
  - Green, Lila (Box 7)
  - Gruber, Stephen (Box 7)
  - Hammelof, Karen (Box 7)
  - Hayes, Daniel (Box 7)
  - Hayman, James (Box 7)
  - Herman, Liz (Box 7)
  - Hollenberg, Emily (Box 7)
  - Hutchinson, Ray (Box 7)
  - Jakubowiak, Andrej (Box 7)
  - Johnson, Timothy (Box 7)
  - Kalem Kerian, Greg (Box 7)
  - Kaminski, Mark (Box 7)
  - Khan, Rodriquez (Box 7)
  - LeClaire, Gini (Box 7)
  - Levine, John (Box 7)
  - Lichter, Allen (Box 7)
  - Lin, John (Box 7)
  - Maerjaver, Sophia (Box 7)
  - McGuinn, Cornelius (Box 7)
  - Milliron, Kara (Box 7)
  - Montie, James (Box 7)
  - Morris, Sheila (Box 7)
  - Moyad, Mark (Box 7)
  - Mule, Jim (Box 7)
  - Nabel, Gary (Box 7)
  - Nelson, Christine (Box 7)
  - Northouse, Laurel (Box 7)
  - Okoda (Box 7)
  - Orringer, Mark (Box 7)
  - Peterson, Amber (Box 7)
  - Pienta, Ken (Box 7)
  - Pierce, Lori (Box 7)
  - Redman, Bruce (Box 7)
  - Reynolds, Chris (Box 7)
  - Riba, Michelle (Box 7)
  - Rosenthal, Jeff (Box 7)
  - Ross, Charles (Box 7)
  - Rubin, Mark (Box 7)
  - Ruffin, Mark (Box 7)
  - Sanda, Martin (Box 7)
  - Schott, Anne (Box 7)
  - Scott, Shannon (Box 7)
  - Shureiqi, Imad (Box 7)
  - Silver, Sam (Box 7)
  - Silver, Terry (Box 7)
  - Simeone, Diane (Box 7)
  - Solvay, Maxine (Box 7)
  - Spahlinger, Dave (Box 7)
  - Stretcher, Vic (Box 7)
  - Trask, Peter (Box 7)
  - Triola, Chris (Box 7)
  - Uberti, Joseph (Box 7)
  - Vander Woude, Amy (Box 7)
  - Volk, Ruti (Box 7)
  - Vorant (Box 7)
  - Waldinger, Marcy Bohm (Box 7)
  - Warden, Marge (Box 7)
  - Weiss, Steve (Box 7)
  - Wicha, Max (Box 7)
  - Wolf, Gregory (Box 7)
  - Wolf, Stewart (Box 7)
  - Woo, Marlene (Box 7)
  - Yanik, Greg (Box 7)
- Photographs-Topical 1993-2004
  Photographs -- Topical (3 linear feet) (1993-2004; many undated) are arranged alphabetically by individually labeled folders for each event or topic. The majority of folders do not contain dates. Topics range from UMCCC events, medical equipment and procedures, departments involved in UMCCC, support services, and staff members. Topics covered in more detail include UMCCC events, the building of the Cancer Center, the Making Strides Walk, the Spring to Life event, and photographs featured in the publication Update from 1999-2002.
  - Art Fair (Box 8)
  - Benefit Concert with Nina Perlove (Box 8)
  - BMT (Box 8)
  - Bone Mets (Box 8)
  - Breast Care Center (Box 8)
  - Cancer Center Building, 1 volumes with loose photos (Box 8)
    (Ground breaking, renderings, construction, completion)
  - Cancer Center Car (Box 8)
  - Cancer Geriatric Clinic 2000 (Box 8)
  - Cancer Prevention Trial 1999 (Box 8)
  - Chem-Oncology Secretaries 2000 (Box 8)
  - Children (Box 8)
  - Circle of Care Family Retreat (Box 8)
  - Clerks 1998 (Box 8)
  - Colleagues in Care 1994 (Box 8)
  - Development (Box 8)
  - Events, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Exams and Equipment (Box 8)
  - Fertility (Box 8)
  - Finance Research 1999 (Box 8)
  - Girl Scouts with Christmas Gifts 2000-2001 (Box 8)
  - Grief Loss Rounds 2001 (Box 8)
  - Gynecology Oncology (Box 8)
  - Halloween (Box 9)
  - Head and Neck (Box 9)
  - Healing Arts Center (Box 9)
  - Just Among Women 1993 (Box 9)
  - Long Term Follow-Up (Box 9)
  - Lung (Box 9)
  - Lymphoma (Box 9)
  - Making Strides Walk 2003-2004, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Marketing Group (Box 9)
  - MDUC (Box 9)
  - Medical Oncology (Box 9)
  - Melanoma (Box 9)
  - M-Greeter (Box 9)
  - NCI Core Grant 2000 (Box 9)
  - Nursing 2002 (Box 9)
  - Nutrition (Box 9)
  - Orthonics Staff 2000 (Box 9)
  - Palliative Care Program 1999 (Box 9)
  - Pancreatic (Box 9)
  - Parking Attendants (Box 9)
  - Pathology Group 1999 (Box 9)
  - Patient Consult (Box 9)
  - Peds (Box 9)
  - PERC (Patient Education) (Box 9)
  - Personal Touch Boutique (Box 9)
  - Physician (Box 9)
  - Pony Express (Box 9)
  - Procedure (includes BMT harvest) (Box 9)
  - Progress, 1995-2000 (Box 9)
  - PSS (Art therapy) (Box 9)
  - Radiotherapy Machine (Box 9)
  - Retirements (Box 10)
  - Sarcoma (Box 10)
  - Sarcoma (Box 10)
  - Scientific (Box 10)
  - Seagram and Singer brochure (Box 10)
  - Senior Leaders (Wicha, Chang, Waldinger) (Box 10)
  - Spring to Life 1994-1995, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Staff (Box 10)
  - Staff Activities (Box 10)
  - Stereotactic (Box 10)
  - Stuffed Bear Raffle (Box 10)
  - Support Groups (Box 10)
  - Surgery (Box 10)
  - Survivor Events (Box 10)
  - Temping Tables (Box 10)
  - Thoracic (Box 10)
  - Transgenic Animal Care (Box 10)
  - Update, 1999-2002, 6 folders (Box 10)
  - VFW Ladies Auxiliary (Box 10)